A Finding Aid to the Arthur Sinclair Covey Papers, 1882-1960, in the Archives of American Art AAA.covearth
Archives of American Art
Arthur Sinclair Covey papers
1882-1960
AAA.covearth
Archives of American Art
5.7 Linear feet
The papers of mural painter and illustrator Arthur Sinclair Covey measure 5.7 linear feet and date from 1882 to 1960. Found within the papers are biographical material; correspondence with art institutions, patrons, and colleagues; scattered business and financial records; notes and writings by Covey and others, including a transcript of an interview with Covey by a radio station; art work and sketchbooks by Covey and his colleagues including Paul Bransom, Harvey Dunn, and Edward Penfield; project files concering Covey's mural projects; a scrapbook of clippings; additional printed material; and photographs of Covey, family members, colleagues, and art work.
Covey, Arthur Sinclair
Biographical Note
Arthur Sinclair Covey was born June 13, 1877 in Leroy, Illinois, son of Byron and Emeline Edwards Covey. His boyhood was spent in various small towns in Missouri and Kansas. As a teenager in 1893, Covey "made the run" to claim land at the opening of the Cherokee Strip in Oklahoma.
From 1895 to 1896, Covey attended Southwestern College in Winfield, Kansas, followed by three years of study under Frank Duveneck, among others, at the Chicago Art Institute, from which he graduated in 1899. From 1900 to 1901, he worked as a staff artist and art editor for the Indianapolis Press and the Cleveland Plain Dealer. For the next two years, he taught at the Chicago Art Institute and established his own studio.
In 1904, Covey traveled to the Royal Academy in Munich where he was a student of Karl Marr, and, from 1905 to 1908, served as assistant to British mural painter Frank Brangwyn and taught at the London School of Art. In 1908, Covey returned to New York and married Mary Dorothea Sale, with whom he had two children, Margaret Sale Covey and Laird Fortune Covey.
Covey received official recognition for his artwork when he assisted Robert Reid and Jules Guerin on murals for the 1914-1915 Panama-Pacific Exposition and received the Bronze Medal. The following year, Covey completed his first commission to paint murals for the Wichita, Kansas, Library, and continued to work steadily on mural projects for the rest of his career.
Following the death of his wife in 1917, Covey married children's book illustrator Lois Lenski in 1921. They had a son, Stephen John Covey.
In 1925, Covey received the Architectural League's Gold Medal of Honor in Painting for his murals at the Kohler Company. From 1926 to 1929, he served as President of the national Mural Painters Society, and from 1929 to 1942, he taught pictorial composition at the National Academy Schools in New York. From 1938 to 1939, Covey created pierced brass on redwood murals for the exterior of the Contemporary Arts Building at the New York World's Fair. In 1939, he decorated the dome and globe of the Land Plane Building at La Guardia Airport in New York.
In the 1950s, Lois Lenski Covey's failing health required that the couple move permanently to Florida's warmer climate.
Arthur Sinclair Covey died on February 5, 1960, in Tarpon Springs, Florida.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of mural painter and illustrator Arthur Sinclair Covey measure 5.7 linear feet and date from 1882 to 1960. Found within the papers are biographical material; correspondence with art institutions, patrons, and colleagues; scattered business and financial records; notes and writings by Covey and others, including a transcript of an interview with Covey by a radio station; art work and sketchbooks by Covey and his colleagues including Paul Bransom, Harvey Dunn, and Edward Penfield; project files concering Covey's mural projects; a scrapbook of clippings; additional printed material; and photographs of Covey, family members, colleagues, and art work.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into nine series according to type of material and further arranged in chronological order. Oversized material from various series has been housed in Boxes 6-8 and Oversized Folders 9-12, and is noted in the Series Descriptions/Container Listing section at the appropriate folder title with see also/see references.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1925-1960, undated (Box 1, 6; 4 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1915-1960, undated (Box 1, OV 9; 28 folders)
Series 3: Business Records, 1915-1958, undated (Box 1; 14 folders)
Series 4: Notes and Writings, 1923-1958, undated (Box 1; 10 folders)
Series 5: Art Work, 1921-1957, undated (Box 1, 6, OV 9-10; 23 folders)
Series 6: Project Files, 1916-1959 (Box, 1-2, 6, OV 9-12; 68 folders)
Series 7: Scrapbook, 1914-1960 (Box 8; 1 folder)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1882-1959, undated (Box 2-4, 7; 2.4 linear feet)
Series 9: Photographs, 1891-1959, undated (Box 5, 7-8; 21 folders)
Provenance
The Arthur Sinclair Covey papers were donated from 1961 to 1965 by the artist's widow, Lois Lenski Covey.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Bransom, Paul, 1885-; Dunn, Harvey, 1884-1952; Lenski, Lois, 1893-; Penfield, Edward, 1866-1925; Illustrators--Connecticut; Mural painting and decoration--Buildings; Muralists--Connecticut; Painters; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Works of art
- Biographical Material, 1925-1960, undated; Series 1; (Box 1, 6; 4 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical Material consists of genealogical charts, membership cards and certificates, and an award certificate from the Architectural League of New York.
  - Genealogical Information, 1957-1960, undated; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Membership Cards and Certificates, 1927-1959; (See Also Box 6) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Award Certificate, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Three Oversize Membership Certificates, 1930-1953; (See Box 1, F3) (Box 6 (sol))
- Correspondence, 1915-1960, undated; Series 2; (Box 1, OV 9; 28 folders)
  Correspondence is primarily with art institutions, patrons, and includes scattered letters from colleagues including George Bellows, Edwin Howland Blashfield, Frank Brangwyn, Dean Cornwell, Gordon Grant, John Guerin, and Ezra Winter.
  - Correspondence, undated; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1928; (see also OV 9) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Oversized Christmas Card from Charles and Ada Chapman, 1928; (See Box 1, F12 (Box OV 9)
- Business Records, 1915-1958, undated; Series 3; (Box 1; 14 folders)
  Business records include insurance and miscellaneous financial material. Business letters from Floyd Covey reflect the management of Arthur Covey's financial dealings by his younger brother.
  - Insurance Records, 1922-1927 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Accounts Ledger, 1919-1937; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Income Tax Records, 1922-1937 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Mohawk Asbestos Slate Co., Inc. Letters and Receipts, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Business Letters from Floyd Covey, 1941-1949; (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 37-42)
  - Price Lists, 1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1920-1958 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Miscellaneous Business Records, 1915-1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Notes and Writings, 1923-1958, undated; Series 4; (Box 1; 10 folders)
  Notes and writings include a transcript of a radio interview with Covey, miscellaneous lists, typescripts, and poems by William Adams Delano.
  - Transcript of Interview of Covey by Radio Station WNYC, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Membership Lists, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Minutes from Clearwater Art Museum Round Table on Modern Art, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Guestbook, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - List of Guests, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Manuscript "Some Notes on a Six Month's Stay in Europe" by Covey, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Typescript of Speech by Covey at the Dixie Cooley Memorial Exhibition, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Typescript "A Close-Up Commentary on Sir Frank Brangwyn" by Covey, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Poems by William Adams Delano, 1938-1948 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Art Work, 1921-1957, undated; Series 5; (Box 1, 6, OV 9-10; 23 folders)
  This series consists of drawings, paintings, and prints by Covey and his colleagues including noted illustrators Paul Bransom, Harvey Dunn, George Hill, A. P. Keller, Frank Leyendecker, Howard McCormick, Alice Harold Murphy, Edward Penfield, William Traher, and Ezra Winter.
  - Sketchbook 1, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Sketchbook 2, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Sketchbook 3, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Sketchbook 4, undated; (see also Box 6) (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Sketchbook 5, undated; (see also Box 6) (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Designs for Stencils to be Cut in Metal for a Residential Lamp, undated; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 61-63)
  - Miscellaneous Drawings by Covey, undated; (2 folders; see also Box 6) (Box 1, Folder 64-65)
  - Oil Sketches and Prints by Covey, undated; (See Also Box 6 and OV 9) (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Woodcut by Unidentified Artist and Drawing by a Child, 1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Drawing by Frank Leyendecker, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Wood Engraving by Howard McCormick, undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Etching by Alice Harold Murphy, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Art Work by Edward Penfield including booklet "Spanish Ways" containing original drawings, undated; (See Also Box 6 and OV 10) (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Lithograph by William Traher, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Oversize Sketcbook 4, undated; (See Box 1, F59) (Box 6 (sol))
  - Oversize Sketchbook 5, undated; (See Box 1, F60) (Box 6 (sol))
  - Fifteen Oversize Miscellaneous Drawings by Covey, undated; (See Box 1, F64-65) (Box 6 (sol))
  - Oversize Scrapbook of Drawings by Covey, undated; (See Box 1, F64-65) (Box 6 (sol))
  - Three Oversize Oil Sketches, Six Etchings, undated; (See Box 1, F66) (Box 6 (sol))
  - Six Lithographs by Covey, undated; (See Box 1, F66) (Box 6 (sol))
  - Oversize Drawings by Ade de Bethune, Paul Bransom, George Hill, A. P. Keller, and Ezra Winter; an Oil Sketch by Harvey Dunn; and five works of art by Edward Penfield, 1921-1957, undated (Box 6 (sol))
  - Oversize Lithograph Opening of the Cherokee Strip by Covey, undated; (See Box 1, F66) (Box OV 9)
  - Three Oversize Posters by Edward Penfield, undated; (See Box 1, F71) (Box OV 10)
- Project Files, 1916-1959; Series 6; (Box, 1-2, 6, OV 9-12; 68 folders)
  Project files contain contracts, correspondence, receipts, notes, art work, printed material, and photographs documenting Covey's various mural painting projects. The file concerning the New York World's Fair includes a cut-out paper design for one of the pierced brass murals used to decorate the Community Arts Building, and booklets "New York World's Fair Bulletin" and "Futurama."
  - Lord & Taylor Murals, New York, New York, 1916-1925 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - William Filene & Sons Mural, Boston, Massachusetts, 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Orthopedic Hospital Murals, Orange, New Jersey, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Kohler Company Industrial Murals, Kohler, Wisconsin, 1923-1926; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 76-78)
  - Norton Company Murals and Windows, Worcester, Massachusetts, 1925-1959; (15 folders; see also OV 11) (Box 1, Folder 79-93)
  - Lasalle and Koch Company Murals, Toledo, Ohio, 1926-1927; (see also Box 6) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Kohler Company Showroom Murals, Kohler, Wisconsin, 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Textile High School Murals, New York, New York, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Willys Overland Company Auditorium Murals, Toledo, Ohio, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - John Brown Post Office Mural, Torrington, Connecticut, 1929-1938; (4 folders; see also OV 12) (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
  - Squibb Building Ceiling Mural, New York, New York, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - War Memorial Auditorium Murals, Worcester, Massachusetts, 1930-1938; (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 10-14)
  - Post Office Murals, Bridgeport, Connecticut, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Guaranty Trust Bank Mural, Worcester, Massachusetts, 1936-1941; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - New York World's Fair Community Arts Building Pierced Brass Mural, New York, New York, 1937-1940; (12 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-29)
  - North Beach (La Guardia) Airport Rotunda Mural and Globe Design, New York, New York, 1938-1939; (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 30-33)
  - Post Office Mural, Anderson, South Carolina, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - George Jeppson Residence Mural, Brookfield, Massachusetts, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Horace Mann School Library Mural, Riverdale, New York, 1945-1947; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
  - Trinity Lutheran Church Ceiling Mural, Worcester, Massachusetts, 1947-1957; (7 folders; see also OV 9) (Box 2, Folder 38-44)
  - Wisconsin Centennial Display Murals, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 1948; (2 folders; see also Box 6) (Box 2, Folder 45-46)
  - Kohler Company Showroom Plaques, Kohler, Wisconsin, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Sixteen Oversize Photographs of Art Work for Lasalle and Koch Company Murals Project File, 1926-1927; (See Box 2, F1) (Box 6 (sol))
  - Sixteen Oversize Reproductions of Art Work for Wisconsin Centennial Display Murals Project File, 1948; (See Box 2, F45-46) (Box 6 (sol))
  - Two Oversize Drawings and Three Blueprints for Trinity Lutheran Church Ceiling Mural Project File, 1947-1957; (See Box 2, F38-44) (Box OV 9)
  - Thirteen Oversize Lithographs for Norton Company Murals and Windows Project File, 1925-1959; (See Box 1, F79-93) (Box OV 11)
  - Five Oversize Drawings for John Brown Post Office Mural, Torrington, Connecticut Project File, 1929-1938; (See Box 2, F5-8) (Box OV 12)
- Scrapbook, 1914-1960; Series 7; (Box 8; 1 folder)
  A scrapbook contains clippings, booklets, printed invitations, and 2 photographs of an exhibition.
  - Scrapbook, 1914-1960 (Box 8 (sol), Folder 1)
- Printed Material, 1882-1959, undated; Series 8; (Box 2-4, 7; 2.4 linear feet)
  Printed material consists of clippings, including some issues of Scribner Magazine, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Covey and others, prospectuses, reproductions of art work, a program, printed souvenirs from a trip to Italy, miscellaneous brochures and booklets, including Color Studies of the Exposition City, World's Fair (Chicago) in Pictures and Magic in the Night concerning the Golden Gate International Exposition. Books concern art-related topics including four about the work of Frank Brangwyn.
  - Clippings, undated; (see also Box 7) (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Clippings, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Clippings, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Clippings, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Clippings, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Clippings, 1906; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 53-55)
  - Clippings, 1907; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 56-57)
  - Clippings, 1910-1912 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Clippings, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Clippings, 1920-1922 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Clippings, 1923-1925 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Clippings, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Clippings, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Clippings, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Clippings, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Clippings, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1936; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
  - Clippings, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1939; (see also Box 7) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1940-1948 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Covey, 1925-1958, undated; (9 folders) (Box 3, Folder 16-24)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1912-1959, undated; (12 folders) (Box 3, Folder 25-36)
  - Prospectuses, 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Reproductions of Art Work by Covey, 1908-1911, undated; (2 folders; see also Box 7) (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
  - Reproductions of Art Work by Frank Brangwyn, undated; (see also Box 7) (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Reproductions of Art Work by Others, 1882-1938, undated; (3 folders; see also Box 7) (Box 3, Folder 41-43)
  - Program for the Victory Dinner and Dance of the Division of Pictorial Publicity, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Printed Souvenirs from Travel to Italy, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, 1895-1936; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 46-47)
  - Miscellaneous Booklets, 1915-1960 undated; (8 folders) (Box 3, Folder 48-55)
  - Book History of Illustration, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Book Paintings and Illustrations by Edwin Austin Abbey, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Book The Art of the Exposition by Eugen Neuhaus, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Book New Salmagundi Papers, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Book Art and Industry, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Book Modern Masters of Etching: Frank Brangwyn, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Book Frank Brangwyn and His Work by Walter Shaw-Sparrow, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Book The Beaux-Arts Boys on the Boulevards, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Book The British Empire Panels by Frank Brangwyn, R.A., 1937 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Book Century Memorials, 1939, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Book National Gallery of Art Preliminary Catalogue of Paintings and Sculpture, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Book Works of Art, Silver, and Furniture Belonging to the Century Association by Charles Downing Lay and Theodore Bolton, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Book The Water-Colours of Frank Brangwyn, R.A., 1867-1956 by Cyril G. E. Bunt, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Two Oversize Clippings, 1939, undated; (See Box 3, F11) (Box 7 (sol))
  - Oversize Reproductions of Art Work by Covey, 1908-1911, undated; (See Box 3, F38-39) (Box 7 (sol))
  - Oversize Reproductions of Art Work by Frank Brangwyn, undated; (See Box 3, F40) (Box 7 (sol))
  - Oversize Reproductions of Art Work by Others, 1913-1925, undated; (See Box 3, F41-43) (Box 7 (sol))
  - Oversize Book The Historical paintings in the Hall of the Worshipful Company of Skinners, 1909 (Box 7 (sol))
- Photographs, 1891-1959, undated; Series 9; (Box 5, 7-8; 21 folders)
  Photographs are primarily of Covey, family members, colleagues, art-related events, and art work. Album 1 contains photographs of Covey family members and Frank Brangwyn with his art class. Album 2 contains photographs of Covey in his studio and a drawing for the New York World's Fair murals. Albums 3 and 4 contain photographs of Covey's murals. There are also photographs of Sir Alfred East, Morris Henry Hobbs, Charles Battell Loomis, Alfred Loomis, Fred Dana Marsh, Clarence Millet, John Norton, Eugene Savage, Edward Trumbell, and group photographs of Salmagundi Club Dinners for Charles S. Chapman and for Vincent A. Svoboda.
  - Photograph Album 1, 1891-1959, undated; (4 folders) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 1-4)
  - Photographs of Colleagues, 1905-1948, undated; (See Also Box 7) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Models, undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 6)
  - Photograph Album 3, 1939, undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 7)
  - Photograph Album 4, 1946 (Box 5 (hol), Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Art Work by Covey, undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Art Work by C. Y. Turner, undated; (5 folders) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 10-14)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of Art Work by Others, undated; (2 folders; see also Box 7) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 15-16)
  - Travel Photographs, undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 17)
  - Photographs of an Unidentified Building, undated (Box 5 (hol), Folder 18)
  - Three Oversize Photographs of Colleagues, 1930-1938; (See Box 5, F5) (Box 7 (sol))
  - Miscellaneous Oversize Photographs of Art Work by Others, undated; (See Box 5, F15-16) (Box 7 (sol))
  - Photograph Album 2, 1906-1957, undated (Box 8 (sol), Folder 2)